Steve Marshall

Email / Personal website / GitHub profile

Technology leader with deep technical knowledge. Extensive development, operations and delivery experience across a range of sectors, including government, travel, and media. Uses code and design thinking to improve systems and the teams who build them.

Employment history

Head of Hosting at Ministry of Justice (https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/ministry-of-justice)

December 2017–Present

- Leading a team of 70 staff across 3 locations to develop and operate a world-class, cloud hosting platform on AWS and Azure.
- o I set the Ministry of Justice's hosting strategy. As part of this, we are moving around 500 user-facing services to cloud-native hosting. So far this has saved £10m over three years, and because of being able to close contracts as they end, is predicted to save a further £30m/year over the next 5 years.
- Managing a budget of ~£25m/year and contracts with ~30 suppliers, ensuring value for money while delivering our strategy.
- Ensuring delivery of high quality infrastructure services underpinning those 500 user-facing services, including managing, coaching, and mentoring product teams in site reliability engineering, automation, and DevOps practices.

Head of Engineering at Ministry of Justice (https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/ministry-of-justice)

January 2017-April 2018

Led ~150 Python, Java, front-end, Ruby, and operations engineers across 4 locations, and was responsible for technical standards, management, recruitment, and culture.

Improved engineering quality by introducing organisation-wide standards through automation, providing embedded, long-term **coaching for under-performing teams** and individuals, and recruiting technical leads across the organisation. **Improved hiring procedures**, increasing quality of candidates and diversity of engineering staff.

Technical Architect at Ministry of Justice (https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/ministry-of-justice) September 2014—December 2016

Responsible for **technical design and development of digital services** for the UK's National Offender Management Service.

Led development of a service to allow prisoners to receive money from friends and family electronically (Python/Django) from discovery through to public beta, and integration of a service to allow prisoners' friends and family to book visits online (Ruby on Rails) with the legacy prison service backend (Oracle). These included developing prototypes, technical spikes, interaction/experience design reviews to ensure the service best met users' needs.

Technical Architect at Tizaro Supply

March 2014-July 2014

Led infrastructure architecture design and development (Puppet, Python, PHP) for a startup targeting the industrial supply market.

Director of Design at Expedia Affiliate Network (https://expediaaffiliate.com/)

December 2012-March 2014

Led a team **applying user-centred design techniques to APIs** (REST, SOAP, RPC) and user interfaces across Expedia Affiliate Network to speed on-boarding of new partners to support the \$2bn/year partner network.

Previous roles

- o Senior software developer at Expedia Affiliate Network (October 2011-December 2012): Ruby, Chef, Java
- o Senior web developer at Yahoo! (January 2010-September 2011): PHP, Perl, Front-end
- Web developer at Yahoo! (October 2006–December 2009): PHP, Perl, Front-end
- o Software engineer at Systematic Software Engineering (June 2006–October 2006): C#, .NET Framework
- Web developer at Fujitsu Siemens Computers (July 2002-May 2006): C#, .NET Framework

Other interests

- o I am currently building prototypes of two iOS apps (using Swift, SwiftUI, and UIKit) because I have long been interested in iOS app development, but have only recently come up with product ideas that piqued my interest. The first uses OCR and machine learning to allow users to collaboratively curate a cloud-synced index of content. The second allows users to annotate and otherwise prepare collections of images to train CoreML object detection models with CreateML.
- I attend and speak at technology conferences. Notable talks include "Don't Touch the Monolith" at O'Reilly Software Architecture London 2016 and "We Can Mirror It for You Wholesale" at WXG 2014
- I have taken part in five /dev/forts: the most successful product we have built is Spacelog, a site for exploring the stories of early space exploration from the original transcripts.

Education and professional training

- Institute Certified Training Professional from BCS and IITT
- BSc Computer Science & Engineering with First Class Honours from University of Surrey